A Guide to the Edwin Embree papers FA033
Rockefeller Archive Center
Edwin Embree papers
1925-1930
Rockefeller Archive Center
Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
FA033
0.35 Cubic Feet 1 document case
Biographical / Historical
Edwin Embree (1883-1950) was born in Osceola, Nebraska, and lived as a youth in Colorado, Wyoming and Kentucky. He graduated from Yale University in 1906 with a B.A. and then joined the staff of the New York Sun as a cub reporter assigned to police stations and theaters. In 1907 he accepted a position as assistant editor of the Yale Alumni Weekly and remained at Yale in a variety of administrative capacities until 1917. While at New Haven he continued his studies in philosophy and education and received an M.A. in 1913.
In 1917 Mr. Embree joined The Rockefeller Foundation as Secretary under George E. Vincent. Interested in interracial relations, race development, human biology, and cultural anthropology, Embree became Director of the newly created Division of Studies in 1925, and developed some of these interests. He remained in that position until 1927 when he filled the position of Vice President of the Foundation.
Pursuing his interests in interracial relations in 1927, Embree became Director of the Rosenwald Fund, a group which made appropriations to agencies working in the area of Negro welfare. After the depression the Fund concentrated on research and planning in connection with farm tenant problems. Several articles were written as a result of these studies which led to Federal legislation and the establishment of the Farm Security Administration. Having expended its resources, the Rosenwald Fund terminated in 1948. Embree then became President of the Liberian Foundation, a joint American-Liberian organization which assisted in the advancement of health, welfare and education in that country.
Mr. Embree was the author of "Brown America, the story of a New Race," 1931; "Prospecting for Heaven," 1932; "American Negroes: A Handbook," 1932; "Indians of the Americas," 1939; "Brown Americans: the Story of a Tenth of the Nation," 1943; "Thirteen Against the Odds," 1944; and co-author of "Human Biology and Race Welfare," 1930.
Scope and Contents
Important subjects covered in this collection include: the early history and interrelationships of the Rockefeller Foundation, General Education Board, Rockefeller Sanitary Commission, China Medical Board, International Health Board, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; and the 1928 reorganization of the Foundation.
Among the correspondents are Edwin Embree and George E. Vincent.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for scholarly research without restriction.
File Plan
Former Classification: IV 2A 08
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers of Edwin Embree were deposited with The Rockefeller Foundation Archives in August, 1967, by Mrs. Edward (Edwina Embree) Devereux. She gave the papers as an unrestricted gift to the Rockefeller Foundation on January 10, 1971.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers); Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; China Medical Board (U.S); Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.)
- Correspondence, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Rockefeller Foundation - General Bulletins, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Rockefeller Programs - Early History, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Family Journal - Draft, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Family Journal, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "The Science of Human Biology in New Zealand and Australia", 1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Report of the Biological Sciences in Japan", 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Articles and Speeches, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Edwin Embree photographs, 1012; 3 folders
  Biographical / Historical
  Edwin Embree (1883-1950) was born in Osceola, Nebraska, and lived as a youth in Colorado, Wyoming and Kentucky. He graduated from Yale University in 1906 with a B.A. and then joined the staff of the New York Sun as a cub reporter assigned to police stations and theaters. In 1907 he accepted a position as assistant editor of the Yale Alumni Weekly and remained at Yale in a variety of administrative capacities until 1917. While at New Haven he continued his studies in philosophy and education and received an M.A. in 1913.
  In 1917 Mr. Embree joined The Rockefeller Foundation as Secretary under George E. Vincent. Interested in interracial relations, race development, human biology, and cultural anthropology, Embree became Director of the newly created Division of Studies in 1925, and developed some of these interests. He remained in that position until 1927 when he filled the position of Vice President of the Foundation.
  Pursuing his interests in interracial relations in 1927, Embree became Director of the Rosenwald Fund, a group which made appropriations to agencies working in the area of Negro welfare. After the depression the Fund concentrated on research and planning in connection with farm tenant problems. Several articles were written as a result of these studies which led to Federal legislation and the establishment of the Farm Security Administration. Having expended its resources, the Rosenwald Fund terminated in 1948. Embree then became President of the Liberian Foundation, a joint American-Liberian organization which assisted in the advancement of health, welfare and education in that country.
  Mr. Embree was the author of "Brown America, the story of a New Race," 1931; "Prospecting for Heaven," 1932; "American Negroes: A Handbook," 1932; "Indians of the Americas," 1939; "Brown Americans: the Story of a Tenth of the Nation," 1943; "Thirteen Against the Odds," 1944; and co-author of "Human Biology and Race Welfare," 1930.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Photographs, slides, and other images are open for scholarly research.
  RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
  Collection is open for scholarly research. Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
  Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
  Embree, Edwin R. (Edwin Rogers)
  - Australian Aborigines, Mounted on board, captions on back, severely faded, yellowed (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Scope and Contents note
    Indigenous peoples, Australia.
  - Australian Aborigines, 3 mounted on board, with captions, all severely faded (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stone Mountain, Georgia, Mounted on board with captions, severely faded (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Sculpture, landscapes.